<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ajmacdonald/Orlando_DToC/main/CSS/orlando_dtoc2.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 7: Lives in Writing</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p/>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note type="abstract">Sample abstract text</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc sameAs="http://www.cwrc.ca">
				<p>Created from original research by members of CWRC/CSÉC unless otherwise noted.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#" xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#" xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"/></xenoData></teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="prose">
				<head>Introduction</head>
				<p><ref target="#tgenreissue"><ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">Life writing</ref>,
						broadly construed, was at once one of the most welcoming and one of the most
						challenging genres for women writers in the nineteenth century.</ref> The
					nineteenth-century woman writer who planned to write about a life, whether her
					own or someone else’s, faced several challenges. Following <persName key="James Boswell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A88a01f90-9336-4c3b-85f5-032849180b89">James Boswell</persName>’s <title key="The Life of Samuel Johnson" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1218644">Life of <persName>Samuel Johnson</persName></title>
					(1791), often cited as the first modern <ref target="#tgenre_biography">biography</ref>, biography began to coalesce as a genre in the nineteenth
					century. <ref target="#pattitudes">Writing a biography required education and
						training in scholarly methods, which many women writers lacked. Biography is
						rooted in research, and women writers were less likely to have both the
						education to undertake such research and the access to the manuscript and
						book materials that they needed for such work than their male counterparts.
						These challenges faced would-be woman biographers regardless of the gender
						of their proposed subject. <ref type="#tthemetopic">If a woman writer wanted
							to write the life of another woman, these same challenges were
							exacerbated: with the exception of Queens and other figures of
							historical import, women’s lives were not usually well-documented, and
							the would-be biographer of a woman who was not <persName key="Queen Elizabeth I" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5ac060d4-2d7e-4684-a2ab-537a0c86e4ba">Queen Elizabeth I</persName> faced the dual challenge of finding
							sources and writing about another woman’s life when many assumed that
							women’s lives were trivial and not worth documenting.</ref></ref><note type="scholarNote">Juliette Atkinson, <title level="m">Victorian Biography Reconsidered a Study of Nineteenth-Century “Hidden” Lives.</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2010), 146-147.</note> <ref type="#tgenreissue">Indeed, writing about a woman’s life could be seen as an
						unseemly invasion of her privacy; in his <title level="m">Memoirs of the
							Author of A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</title> (1798), <persName key="William Godwin" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8a4d5074-7c65-4376-a5c8-3f804adc1d16">William Godwin</persName> revealed <persName key="Mary Wollstonecraft" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:25504fac-570f-4fb6-bee5-73314bed90ae">Mary Wollstonecraft</persName>’s illegitimate daughter.</ref>
					<ref type="#tgenreissue">The potential for biography to invade women’s privacy
						was not helped by the fact that some of the most popular lives of women in
						the eighteenth century were the vies scandaleuses of courtesans like
							<persName key="Teresia Constantia Phillips" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:eabd259b-1fd7-4a83-9153-f6ada722f993">Teresia Constantia Phillips</persName> and <persName key="Laetitia Pilkington" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:850338f6-0641-471c-83e2-718d467a96c8">Laetitia Pilkington</persName>.</ref><note type="scholarNote">Frances
						Wilson, “Romantic Autobiography.” In The Cambridge Companion to
						Autobiography, edited by Maria DiBattista and Emily O. Wittman (New York:
						Cambridge UP, 2014), 71. See also Atkinson, Victorian Biography, 147.</note>
					<ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">Autobiography</ref>, a term that was coined
					at the end of the eighteenth century in 1797 and confidently used by 1809,<note type="scholarNote">Linda Peterson, Traditions of Victorian Women’s
						Autobiography: The Poetics and Politics of Life Writing, (Charlottesville:
						University of Virginia Press, 1999), 3.</note> developed alongside <ref target="#tgenre_biography">biography</ref>, and even women who sought to
					write about their own lives from their own perspective faced the notion that it
					was unseemly for women to centre themselves. The situation was more difficult
					for working class women writers, who tended to be less literate than both
					working class men and middle-class women, and who wrote, by one estimate, only
					one in ten working class <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiographies</ref> in the period.<note type="scholarNote">For literacy,
						see <persName>Jane Rendall</persName>, “A Short Account of my Unprofitable Life”: Autobiographies
						of Working Class Women in Britain c. 1775-1845, In Women’s Lives / Women’s
						Times: New Essays on Auto/biography, edited by Trev Lynn Broughton and Linda
						R. Anderson (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1997), 32. For an
						overview of Victorian working class writing, see Florence Boos, Memoirs of
						Victorian Working-Class Women: The Hard Way Up (New York: Palgrave
						Macmillan, 2017), 2.</note> Very few of these were published in the
					nineteenth century, and over half of the extant working class women’s <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiographies</ref> remain in
						manuscript.<note type="scholarNote">Boos, Memoirs of Victorian Working-Class
						Women, 2. Boos notes that a few more autobiographical writings of working
						class Victorian women have been uncovered since these numbers were
						calculated.</note>
					<ref target="#pnonsurvival">Indeed, not all women’s life writing survived:
							<persName key="Elizabeth Inchbald" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:b6be4731-d790-4e8a-9f8a-9d1c28455b3c">Elizabeth Inchbald</persName> worked for years writing her life’s story
						in the final years of her life, but encountered so many difficulties with
						publishers who were afraid that the book would be too scandalous or not
						scandalous enough, that she had the manuscript destroyed upon her
						death.</ref></p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
